A Guide to the IAWA Small Collections, 1907-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- Persons and Associations
  - Hook, Mary Rockwell, papers, 1915-1991, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    1877-1978. Residential Architect in Kansas City, Missouri, and architect of the Pine Mountain Settlement School in Harlan County, Kentucky. Collection includes photocopies of her autobiography, This and That, articles about her life and work, and obituaries. Also includes audio cassettes of an interview of Mary Rogers of Pine Mountain by Louise Chawla about Hook's life and career. The Kentucky Oral History Society retains copyright and literary rights to the interview.
  - Hooker, Marjorie Mead (Peggy), biographical information, 1947-2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    1925-2006, Architect of New Mexico. Received Bachelor of Architecture degree from University of Texas (1947) where she was the only woman in her graduating class. After graduating Hooker worked in various offices in Texas and California until she settled in New Mexico where she was an Associate with McHugh and Hooker, Bradley P. Kidder and Associates (1955-1965). She opened her own practice briefly from 1966-1967, until she joined Flatow, Moore, Bryan and Fairburn (1968-1988) to work with Max Flatow on the Albuquerque Urban Renewal Project. She had many firsts attached to her name: first woman to become a corporate member of the Albuquerque Chapter, AIA; she was also the first woman elected president of that chapter (1984); first woman to serve on the New Mexico Board of Examiners for Architects. Collection includes clippings, memorial service material, New Mexico Women’s Hall of Fame Nomination form, and photocopies of various awards received by Hooker.
  - Hosken, Franziska Porges [Fran P.], papers, 1992-1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Publisher and editor of Women's International Network News and a consultant to International Women's Development and Communication, Housing and Urbanization International. Earned her Master of Architecture degree at the Harvard Graduate School of Design in 1944. Resident of Lexington, Massachusetts. Papers consist of a curriculum vitae compiled in 1992, three copies of the Women's International Network News (1994, 1997-1998), and a copy of her book The Language of Cities: A Visual Introduction to the Form and Function of the City (Schenkman Publishing Company, Inc., Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1972) [HT153 .H65 1972 c.2].
  - Hubacher, Annemarie, project list, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Architect of Zurich, Switzerland. Collection consists of a list of architectural designs that Hubacher was involved in.
  - Huber, Verena, biographical material, 1989, 1994-1997 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Born 1938. Interior designer of Zurich, Switzerland, and former president of VSI, the Swiss Association of Interior Designers. Papers include a curriculum vitae, photocopies of articles about her work, and other biographical information.
  - Ison, Leonara, obituaries, 1996-1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Although Ison did not build, she was the first woman to win scholarships at the Bartlett School of Architecture, London University, England, and was a successful illustrator of architecture books.
  - Jauch-Stolz, Monika, papers, 1984 and undated, Extent: 0.3 cubic feet (Box 5, Box 11)
    Born 1954. Architect of Luzerne, Switzerland, and member of the Societe d'Ingenieurs et Architectes. Papers include a curriculum vitae, photos of jewelry she has created, interiors and exteriors of her architectural designs, and copies of architectural drawings she designed with her husband, Martin Jauch.
  - Jirmunsky, Galina, papers, 1950-1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    1926-2010. Russian modernist architect. Collection contains 36 original photographs of designs/drawings/built structures by Jirmunsky; a portrait; and a biographical file written by her husband Feliks Aronovich Novikov, Ph.D. (also an architect who designed/built the Palace of Pioneers on Lenin's Hills (now Sparrow Hills) in Moscow) with commentary on each of the numbered photographs.
  - Kazakova, Liumila, article, 2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Russian architect. Collection contains an article featuring Kazakova's design for the Pyatnitski Fish Market from the Annual published by the Moscow Branch of the International Academy of Architecture in 2002.
  - Keichline, Anna Wagener, papers, 1991-2004, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 18)
    1889-1943. Architect and inventor from Bellefonte, Pennsylvania. First registered woman architect in Pennsylvania and inventor of the K-brick. Designed the Decker Home in Bellefonte. Papers include a copy of an article by her, "Modern Wall Construction" from the 1932 issue of The Clay-Worker, information about her ideas concerning kitchen design, copies of patents for a combination sink and laundry tub, photographs, and biographical information. Added in 2002 biographical materials authored, or collected by, her niece Nancy Perkins. Includes a CD-ROM documenting her life in application for state marker, articles and exhibit programs. Also has material on VT Imagebase. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
  - Kemp, Diane Legge, biographical material, 1985-1989, 1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Born 1949. Principal of DLK Architecture, Inc. of Chicago, Illinois. Former partner of Skidmore, Owings & Merrill in Chicago and former board member of the Chicago Chapter of the American Institute of Architects. Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Papers include a curriculum vitae, a photograph of Kemp, articles (1985-89) about her work, and slides of structures she has designed.
  - Kennedy, Louise St. John, biographical material, 1988 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Born 1950. First woman to be appointed to the Architects Board of Western Australia, and designer of the Perth Mosman Park Tea Rooms, the Pines Business Centre in Cottesloe, and numerous other structures in Western Australia. Papers include articles (1988) about her work and an extensive curriculum vitae detailing her designs and projects, honors, published work, and memberships.
  - Keremidarska, Svetlana Lazarova, curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Born 1950. Russian landscape architect.
  - Khazanova, Vigdalia, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Khazanova is an architectural historian. She earned her masters degree in art history from Moscow State University in 1948. Her collection includes two handwritten manuscripts and a book titled Sovetskaia arkhitektura pervykh let Oktiabria. 1917-1925 [Soviet architecture during the first years after the October, 1917-1925] donated by her son and architect, Mikhail Khazanov. The book is cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and is available through the Special Collections Reading Room.
  - Khokhlova, Larisa, publications, 1988-1992, 2004 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Born 1926. Russian architect, graduated from Moscow Architecture Institute in 1951. Collection contains list of publications, photos of book covers. Three books about building houses and public buildings in ADDISON library catalog.
  - Kingsley, Karen, article, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Kingsley is a professor of architectural history at Tulane University. This collection consists of an article that she wrote about architect Mary Mykolyk.
  - Kiss, Katalin, essay, 1993, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Bound essay by Kiss, "The Character, the City and the Character of the City," 33 pages ca. 1993
  - Kliass, Rosa Grena, biographical materials, 2009, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 20)
    Landscape architect of São Paulo, Brazil and founder of the Brazilian Association of Landscape Architects (ABAP). Kliass graduated from the University of São Paulo's Faculty of Architecture and Urbanism program with her first degree in 1955 and a master's degree in 1989. Kliass established her own practice in 1970 and taught landscape architecture and urban design at Mackenzie University in São Paulo, the Catholic University of Parana, and São Paulo State. In addition to practicing and teaching, Kliass has served as a consultant for several government institutions. Materials consist of a bound curriculum vitae and a bound guide to Kliass' consulting business, including a list of projects, clients, publications, exhibitions, and awards.
    Kliass, Rosa Grena, 1932-
  - Klingelhofer, Petra, portfolios, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    Born 1958. Architect of Stuttgart, Germany. Materials consist of four portfolios with photocopies of sketches featuring landscapes and nudes, and two projects in which she was involved.
  - Koci, Ilse, papers, 1962-1976 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5, Box 14)
    Born 1919. Architect of Vienna, Austria, and designer of many structures in that city. Collection includes a curriculum vitae; eleven photographs (1962-76) of buildings she has designed; an elevation (1969) of Unido Wettbewerb; and a copy of notes of "Research upon the Possibility of a Pedestrian Zone" with preliminary sketches, plans, elevations, and perspectives.
  - Koci-Montanari, Silvia, sketches, 1984-1986, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 11)
    Architect and artist of Rome, Italy. Eleven ink sketches of building exteriors in Austria and Italy.
  - Korobina, Irina M., papers, 2009, 2011, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Graduated from the Moscow Institute of Architecture (1980). Korobina is Director of the State Museum of Architecture in Moscow (2011-). She was formally director of the Center of Contemporary Architecture (C:CA) (2001-2011) whose activities included the production of a weekly television series (2001-2004) titled Architecture Gallery which was supported by the Ford Foundation and authored and narrated by Korobina. Collection includes a greeting card to Anna P. Sokolina in honor of International Women's Day, March 2011 and printouts from Russian media referencing Korobina's appointment to Director of the State Museum of Architecture.
  - Koulagina, Helen A., papers, 2012 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 20)
    Architect and artist from Moscow, Russia. Graduate of the Moscow Architectural Institute. Koulagina serves as a mentor for the Russian Academy of Arts and maintains membership in several international organizations, including the International Art Fund and the Union of Artists of Russia. Awarded the Laureate of the XI National Artiada of Russia in 2011. Materials include two biographical brochures, a photograph of the architect, a postcard featuring a stuio portrait, and 8 small prints of her architectural paintings.
    Kulagina, Helena Albertovna
  - Kuhler, Ingeborg, papers, 1987-1990, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 11)
    Born 1943, Dachau, Germany. The collection consists of color photomontages and black and white photomontages of two buildings designed by Kuhler: the Studios for the Broadcasting Corporation of Southern Germany, 1987; and the State Museum of Technology and Labor, 1990, both in Mannheim. Also included is a brief biography of Kuhler. Inventory available.
  - Kurian, Elizabeth George, curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 5)
    Born 1969. Architect in India. Collection includes curriculum vitae.
  - Lambert, Phyllis, biographical material, 1998, 2006, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Bachelor degree from Vassar in 1948, master's degree from Illinois Institute of Technology in 1968. Worked on the Seagram Building with Mies van der Rohe. Founder in 1979 and director until 1999 of the Canadian Center for Architecture/Centre Canadian d'Architecture. Lambert was the consulting architect to Peter Rose for the CCA building project, 1984-1989. In addition to directing the CCA, she won recognition for both her original designs and her restoration work. The collection contains a biography outlining Lambert's career and a notice about her receiving the National Building Museum's 2006 Scully Prize.
  - Landry, Jane L., publications, 1990, 1997 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1936. Architect of Dallas, Texas. Principal of Landry & Landry Architects & Planners, and a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Publication and résumé of her firm.
  - Lang Jakob, Evelyne, papers, 1987-1992, 1998,2002, and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1960. Swiss architect practicing in Bern, Switzerland. Educated at the Federal Polytechnical School of Zurich, where she earned her Ph.D. in science in 1993. Member of the Swiss Organization of Engineers and Architects and the Union Internationale des Femmes Architectes. Papers consist of curriculum vita and articles (1987 and 1989) by Lang Jakob from the magazines Archithese and Actualite; a copy of her thesis written in 1992 for the architecture department at the Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (where she did post-graduate work), entitled "Les Premieres Femmes Architectes de Suisse;" and a copy of the magazine Baudoc Bulletin (February 1998), with an article by Lang Jakob, "Neolithische Architektur aus Sudanatolien, Zypern und Malta" (in French and German). Member of the IAWA Board of Advisors, 1995-2001.
  - Lari, Yasmeen, curriculum vitae and CD, 1992, 2003, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    First registered woman architect in Pakistan (1963) and Principal of Lari Associates, Architects & Urban Designers. Elected to IAWA Board of Advisors in 2002. Collection includes a 1992 curriculum vitae and a CD containing approximately 240 JPG images of six of Lari's completed projects taken by Marcia Feuerstein in 2003. Also has material in VT Imagebase.
  - Lassmann, Edith, publications and photographs, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of Vienna, Austria. Materials include two brochures of a hospital and of her architectural firm; an article, "Das Frauenstudium an den Technischen Hochschuelen Wien und Graz," from Frauenstudium und Akademische Frauenarbeit in Osterreich; and photographs of her designs of a hydroelectric plant in the Austrian Alps and of a children's center in Vienna.
  - Lemos, Maria Joana Viana de, drawings, Extent: 3.0 cubic feet (Oversize 15.1-15.2)
    Architect of Coimbra, Portugal. Papers consist of two notebooks of architectural drawings and construction specifications for health centers in Tondela and Vagos, Portugal, of which de Lemos was architect.
  - Levine, Sally, papers, 1995-1998, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of Chicago, Illinois, and co-founder of CARY (Chicks in Architecture Refuse to Yield), a Chicago women architects group. Materials focus on a multi-media exhibit Levine created entitled "ALICE (Architecture Lets in Chicks Except...) Through the Glass Ceiling," which explores the status of women in the field of architecture. The exhibit was shown at the New Langton Arts Gallery in San Francisco from July to September 1995. Documentation of the exhibit, Palladio's Sister, is also included. Materials include literature describing the both exhibits, an audiotape cassette, slides, and Levine's curriculum vitae.
  - Lin, Maya, biographical material, 2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Yale University Alumni Fellows Candidate biography
  - Lipsey-Rahe, Georgina, papers, 1985, 1995, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 6, Box 11)
    Scope and Content note
    Born 1953. Architect of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. A copy of her graduate thesis, "Where Land Meets Water: The Alexandria [Virginia] Performing Arts Center," from Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Includes a curriculum vitae, architectural drawings, and photographs. Additional copy of Lipsey-Rahe's thesis is located in the circulating collection call number: LD5655 V855 1985 L57
  - Loffler, Anthusa, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1957. Architect of Koln, Germany. Materials include photographs and copies of architectural drawings. A book titled The Shakers: life and production of a community in the pioneering days of America: an exhibition was cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and is available through the Special Collections Reading Room.
  - Lourida, Sophia, biographical material, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of Greece. Includes short biography.
  - Lyon, Virginia, papers, 1967, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of New York City. Collection consists of letters to Lyon from the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards regarding changing the wording of her registration certificate from "he" to "she."
  - Macfarlane, Jane, catalogue, 1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of London, Great Britain. Copy of Catalogue of Films and Television Programmes on Architecture, Town Planning and the Environment (1987) compiled and edited by Macfarlane.
  - Magee, Fannie, drawings, 1925, Extent: 1.7 cu. ft. (Oversize 12.1-12.2)
    Newcomb College class of 1925. Magee was in the Constructive Design and Interior Decoration Department. Newcomb College, a coordinate college of Tulane University 1886-2006, offered an industrial art program featuring pottery, interior design, furniture making, and many other arts and crafts in an effort to educate women in the "practical side of life" and also to provide employment for women at a time when few opportunities existed. The collection includes 14 original pencil drawings by Magee, include seven furniture studies (five chairs, two tables), six interiors, an exterior courtyard, and a sketch of marigolds. See also Newcomb College Drawings Acc2011-073.
  - Maiz Apellaniz, Marta, curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1959. Architect of Madrid, Spain. Collection consists of a lengthy curriculum vitae with copies of architectural drawings and articles about her work.
  - Mang-Frimmel, Eva, publications and photographs, 1982-1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect of Vienna, Austria. Materials consist of two posters of photographs and architectural designs of structures she and her husband, Karl Mang, have designed together from 1953 to 1984, a book Neue Laden (Verlag Gerd Hatje: Stuttgart. 1981), and two catalogs in which Mang contributed, two brochures, and copies of four magazine articles (1982-1987) in which her work is cited.
  - Marquard, Claudia, posters, 1998, Extent: 1.5 cubic feet (Oversize 7)
    Collection consists of color photomontages of Marquard's commissions in Berlin: the restoration of a group of apartment buildings on Rosenthaler Street and the restoration of a house for Potsdam Gregor. Inventory available. Also has materials located in VT Imagebase.
  - Marquina, Nani, catalog, 2012, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 20)
    Rug designer and entrepreneur in Barcelona, Spain. Marquina's company, "nanimarquina", has won several awards, including the Red Dot Design Award in 2003; the National Design Award and Premi Cambra a la Gestio Empresarial (Chamber Award of Design Management) in 2005; the Principe Felipe Award for Company Excellence in 2007; the Culture National Award of the Generalitat de Catalunya government in 2008; and the FIDEM Award for Entrepreneurial Woman of the Year in 2007. Materials include one 2012 product catalog with biographical information about Nani Marquina and her company.
    Marquina, Nani
  - Marshall-Baker, Anna, papers, 1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Faculty member, Department of Near Environments, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (1992-2001). Member of the Board of Advisors of the IAWA, 1996-1999. The collection consists of an exhibit catalog for Knoll Furniture. Marshall-Baker co-curated the exhibition, entitled "The Knoll Spirit," which was held in Wallace Hall at the College of Human Resources, Virginia Tech, in 1997. See also the exhibitions she curated in the VT ImageBase. Inventory available.
  - Martin, Shelley F., curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Faculty member of the Department of Architecture, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Member of the IAWA Board of Advisors, 1996-1998. Collection contains a curriculum vita.
  - Matrix: Feminist Architectural Co-Operative Limited publications, 1986, 1989, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Non-profit women's architectural cooperative in London, Great Britain, designed to help women's groups and groups that benefit women by finding and assessing potential building sites, aiding in obtaining funding for construction, and making models and giving workshops to help women's groups understand and take part in the design process. Records consist of publications written and published by MATRIX. The following books were cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and are available through the Special Collections Reading Room: Making Space: Women and the Man-Made Environment (1986) [ NA2543.W65 M35 1985], Building for Childcare (1986) [HV851 .B85x 1986], and A Job Designing Buildings (1986).
  - Matsukawa, Junko, firm brochure, 1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 5)
    President of Laboratory for Innovators of Quality of Life based in Tokyo, Japan.
  - Matsuzaki, Eva, biographical material, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Biographical Information and project information sheets for the AIA Earth Day 2000 Top Ten Winner submission C.K. Choi Building for the Institute of Asian Records, University of British Columbia.
  - Mendelsohn, Louise, typescript autobiography, 1954 and undated, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 16)
    Born in Germany in 1894, died 1980, wife of German-American architect Eric Mendelsohn (1887-1953), who was an exponent of German Expressionism and the functional modern look called the "International Style." Collection is a typescript autobiography, "My Life in a Changing World" by Louise Mendelsohn, about her life with her husband, her views on architecture and design, and her attempts to establish what is now the National Building Museum in Washington, D.C. Also includes a typescript proposal by Mendelsohn for the establishment of "A Museum of Architecture" (1954)
  - Meredith, Amaza Lee biographical material, 1994, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    1895-1984. African-American architect in Virginia; professor of Art at Virginia State University. Materials consist of a November 1994 article written for Inform about Meredith's life and work, particularly about her design of her home in Petersburg, Virginia.
  - Merle, Ulla, article, 2003, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Collection includes a 1993 periodical "Hessische Heimat" vol.3, containing an article by Merle of Marburg, Germany about a female architect and monument-caretaker named Anneliese Klappenbach.
  - Miculinic, Sonja, brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Printed brochure containing basic biographical information about Miculinic as well as a listing of exhibitions, reference projects, and competitions she which she participated.
  - Mikic, Vesna, papers, 1987-1990, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6, Oversize 9.1-9.3)
    Born 1954. Facility architect at the Faculty of Architecture of the University in Zagreb, Croatia (formerly Yugoslavia). Received first prize in competitions for urban designs in Zagreb and Krg. Collection consists of architectural drawings and copies of photographs for competitions (1987-1990) in which she submitted entries (urban villas in Zagreb and housing in Belgrade).
  - Møller, Alice Finnerup, poster, 2007, Extent: 2.5 cubic feet (Oversize 20)
    Møller is a practicing architect in Denmark. The collection consists of a poster entitled "A House on the West Coast of Denmark: Identity - Preservation and putting into value of the national heritage." It has written narrative (in English), interior and exterior photos and a photo of architect. Another poster by Møller is part of the UIFA 14th Conference materials.